Barry Commoner Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Barry Commoner Papers 1915-2009 1940-1990
MSS59774
Commoner, Barry, 1917-2012
169,000 items
528 containers plus 16 oversize
217 linear feet
142 digital files (0.39 GB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Biologist, ecologist, and environmental activist. Correspondence, speeches, writings, research files, subject files, organizational files, printed matter, photographs in both physical and digital formats, and other papers documenting Commoner's career as a biologist, ecologist, and environmental activist. Subjects include the physiochemical basis of biological processes, moral obligations of scientists, ecology, and the politics of environmental stewardship.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Commoner, Barry, 1917-2012.; Commoner, Barry, 1917-2012. Closing circle; nature, man, and technology. 1971.; Commoner, Barry, 1917-2012. Making peace with the planet. 1990.; Commoner, Barry, 1917-2012. Poverty of power: energy and the economic crisis. 1976.; Commoner, Barry, 1917-2012. Science and survival. 1966.; Leake, Chauncey Depew, 1896-1978.; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978.; Nader, Ralph.; Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994.; Pigman, William Ward, 1910-; Szent-Györgyi, Albert, 1893-1986.; Wolfle, Dael, 1906-2002.
Organizations
American Association for the Advancement of Science.; Committee for Environmental Information (Saint Louis, Mo.); Greater St. Louis Citizens' Committee for Nuclear Information.; Scientists' Institute for Public Information.; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.; United States. Office of Naval Research.; Washington University (Saint Louis, Mo.)--Faculty.; Washington University (Saint Louis, Mo.). Center for the Biology of Natural Systems.
Subjects
Air pollution.; Air quality.; Biochemistry.; Biology.; Botany.; Civil defense.; Dioxins--Environmental aspects--Italy--Seveso.; Ecology.; Energy consumption.; Energy policy--United States.; Environmental protection.; Environmental responsibility.; Environmentalism.; Genetics.; Human ecology.; Industries--Environmental aspects.; Nature--Effect of human beings on.; Nuclear energy--Technological innovations.; Nuclear energy.; Nuclear weapons--Testing.; Plant physiology.; Pollution.; Population.; Power resources.; Radioactive fallout--Health aspects.; Radioactive fallout.; Science and civilization.; Science--Moral and ethical aspects.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Places
United States--Economic policy--1971-1981.
Occupations
Biologists.; Ecologists.; Environmental activists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Barry Commoner were given to the Library of Congress by Commoner in 1981. Additions to the collection were given by Commoner to the Library in 2011 and 2014.
Transfers
Sound recordings, videocassettes, and filmstrips have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Barry Commoner Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Barry Commoner are open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Access to digital content is available onsite only in the Manuscript Reading Room and requires advanced notice. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
Technical Requirements
Digital files were received as part of the 2019 addition to the papers of Barry Commoner on a CD, and were assigned a unique digital ID number. The content is image files in .jpg format. Use the digital ID number to request access copies of the files. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1917, May 28 Born, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1937 B.A., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1938 M.A., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1940 1942 Biology instructor, Queens College, New York, N.Y.
1941 Ph.D., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1942 Entered United States Naval Reserve
1942 1945 Lieutenant and Research Physiologist, United States Naval Air Force
1946 Married Gloria C. Gordon (divorced)
1946 1947 Associate editor, Science Illustrated
1947 1953 Associate professor of plant physiology, Washington University, St. Louis, Mo.
1953 1976 Professor of plant physiology, Washington University, St. Louis, Mo.; chair, Biology Department, 1965-1969
1957 With Linus Pauling, wrote and distributed to the scientific community an open letter calling for the end of aboveground nuclear weapons testing
1958 Co-founder, Greater St. Louis Citizens’ Committee for Nuclear Information; name changed to Committee for Environmental information, May 1967; ceased operations in 1977
1958 1970 Co-founder, Baby Tooth Survey, St. Louis, Mo., measured increased levels of radioactive strontium-90 in children's teeth due to aboveground nuclear weapons testing
1965 1981 Founder and director, Center for the Biology of Natural Systems, Washington University, St. Louis, Mo.; moved to Queens College, Flushing, N.Y., 1981
1966 Published Science and Survival. New York: Viking
1970, Feb. Appeared on the cover of Time magazine as a spokesman for the environmental movement
1971 Published The Closing Circle: Nature, Man, and Technology. New York: Knopf
1976 Published The Poverty of Power: Energy and the Economic Crisis. New York: Random House
1976 1981 Professor of environmental science, Washington University, St. Louis, Mo.
1979 Published The Politics of Energy. New York: Knopf
1980 Married Lisa Feiner Citizens Party candidate for president
1980 circa 1982 Senior Scientist, Queens College, New York, N.Y.
1990 Published Making Peace with the Planet. New York: Pantheon
2012, Sept. 30 Died, New York, N.Y.
2014 Honored posthumously by Queens College with the renaming of the Center for the Biology of Natural Systems as the Barry Commoner Center for Health and the Environment
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Barry Commoner (1917-2012 ) span the years 1915-2009, with the bulk of the material dating from 1940 to 1990. The collection documents Commoner's career as a biologist, ecologist, writer, and environmental activist. The papers are organized into seven series: Personal File, Speeches and Writings File, Correspondence, Subject File, Organizations File, with a 1990 Addition and a 2019 Addition. Researchers should keep in mind that the additions are sizeable with many repetitions of file names and folder headings from the original accession.
Commoner, one of the founders of the environmental movement and a political activist, was a professor of plant physiology and botany for many years at Washington University in St. Louis, Missouri. He researched and published extensively on the tobacco mosaic virus (for which he received the 1953 Newcomb Cleveland Prize) and the role of free radicals. In addition to his purely scientific publications, Commoner wrote books on environmentalism and the social aspects of science for the general public. Indeed, providing scientific knowledge to the general public was the core of his political activism.
Commoner’s political activism began with opposition to aboveground nuclear weapons testing and the danger of radioactive fallout. In 1957, in collaboration with Linus Pauling, Commoner wrote and distributed a letter calling for an end to nuclear testing. Signed by thousands of scientists, it was presented to the president of the United States and to the United Nations. In 1958 Commoner helped found the Greater St. Louis Committee for Nuclear Information (CNI). The Baby Tooth Survey, conducted by CNI with Commoner as one of the leaders, collected over two hundred thousand baby teeth to measure the rising levels of radioactive strontium-90 in children’s bodies, the result of fallout that had spread across the country from nuclear weapons testing in Nevada. The Baby Tooth Survey attracted wide public attention, generating opposition to the nuclear tests and influencing the signing of the 1963 Nuclear Test Ban Treaty. Commoner considered this the first victory of the environmental movement.
The core of Commoner’s philosophy of environmental activism was already at the heart of the Baby Tooth Survey: a belief that scientists have a moral obligation to explain science to the general public so the public, not just scientists and politicians, can make informed decisions about science policy. He called this the “science information movement.” The other cornerstone of his environmental thinking was his conviction that unless the means of production, especially energy production, changed, environmental degradation could not be stemmed, thus requiring political solutions. With the goal of establishing a new, progressive, environmentally-engaged political party, Commoner ran as the presidential Nominee of the Citizens Party in 1980.
The collection’s series are listed and briefly described below. A fuller description of each series and a list of its contents can be accessed in the series descriptions within the container list.
The Personal File primarily consists of a general correspondence file and telephone logs along with agendas, appointment books, diaries, and notebooks.
The Speeches and Writings File includes drafts and published copies of his scientific writings, drafts and reviews of his books intended for the general public, and items documenting speaking engagements.
The Correspondence series consists of professional correspondence, received and sent, and includes some drafts of outgoing correspondence.
The Subject File contains material identified by topic, personal name, material type, or name of organization.
The Organizations File includes only those organizations that Commoner either founded, had leadership positions in, or was otherwise heavily involved with.
The 1990 Addition is arranged into six subseries: General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Research File, Photographs and Slides, and Miscellany.
The 2019 Addition contains material received in 2011 and 2014. This addition is arranged into four subseries and an oversize: a Clippings File, Research File, Speeches and Writings, and Subject File.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Personal File, 1947-1976
Speeches and Writings File, 1959-1976
Correspondence, 1956-1977
Subject File, 1915-1978
Organizations File, 1919-1980
1990 Addition, 1943-1979
2019 Addition, 1936-2009
Container List
- Personal File, 1947-1976 (Box 1-13)
  The Personal File is primarily comprised of a general correspondence file and telephone logs along with other material documenting Commoner’s activities and appointments. The telephone logs include notes about the content of conversations or messages. The general correspondence is the bulk of the series. For Commoner's professional correspondence, consult the Correspondence series.
  Material types include correspondence, telephone logs, agendas, appointment books, diaries, itineraries, and notebooks.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Agendas and itineraries, 1973-1976, (6 folders) (Box 13)
  - Appointment book, 1965-1968 (Box 13)
  - Diaries and notebooks, 1946-1949, 1965-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - General correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1947-1952, (8 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1953-1955, (6 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1956-1960, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1961-1962, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1972, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1973, (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1974, (6 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1975-1976, (9 folders) (Box 8)
  - Incoming calls with summaries (Box 9)
    - 1972, (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1973-1974, (8 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1975-1976, (8 folders) (Box 11)
  - Outgoing calls with notes, 1972-1973, (6 folders) (Box 12)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1959-1976 (Box 14-179)
  The Speeches and Writings File includes drafts and published copies of his scientific writings, drafts and reviews of his books intended for the general public, items documenting speaking engagements in the chronological file, and related correspondence and production material for publication projects. The book file includes drafts for his bestselling books The Closing Circle (1971), Making Peace with the Planet (1990), The Poverty of Power (1976), and Science and Survival (1966). The files for his scientific articles include research notes, draft writings, and published copies. Both the 1990 Addition and the 2019 Addition have a Speeches and Writings subseries containing related material.
  Material types include draft writings, published articles, book reviews, correspondence, production material, and reports.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of writing or material into the following categories: Article file, Book file, Chronological file of articles and speaking engagements, Drafts file (chronological), Drafts file (by topic or title), Invitations declined or cancelled, Manuscripts reviewed, Newsletters and journals, and Reports.
  - Article file
    - Articles
      - "The Absence of an Electron Spin Resonance in a Complex of FMN Tryptophan," undated (Box 65)
      - Abstracts, 1953-1958, undated (Box 65)
      - Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics journal, manuscripts submitted, 1951-1952 (Box 65)
      - "Auxiliary Infectious Nucleoprotein from Plants Infected with Tobacco Mosaic Virus," 1954 (Box 65)
      - "The Biochemical Basis of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Inectivity," 1958 (Box 65)
      - "The Biochemistry of the Synthesis and Biological Activity of Tobacco Mosaic Virus," 1958-1959 (Box 65)
      - "Biological Activity of Free Radicals," 1957 (Box 65)
      - "The Biological Activity of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Components," 1957-1959 (Box 65)
      - "Biology Today," 1964 (Box 65)
      - "Clinical Application of Electron Spin Resonance," 1962-1963 (Box 65)
      - "Comments on the Apllication of the Electron Spin Resonance Technique in Biology," 1963-1964 (Box 66)
      - "The Desoxyribonucleoprotein of Tobacco Leaf and its Relation with Tobacco Mosaic Virus Infection," undated (Box 66)
      - "DNA and the Chemistry of Inheritance," 1964-1965 (Box 66)
      - "DNA and the Molecular Basis of Self-Duplication," 1964 (Box 66)
      - "The Effect of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Biosynthesis on the Nucleic Acid Content of Tobacco Leaf," 1955 (Box 66)
      - "An Electron Spin Resonance Analysis of the Mechanism of SDH Activity," 1961 (Box 66)
      - "Electron Spin Resonance Spectrometry in the Differential Diagnosis of Jaundice," 1964 (Box 66)
      - "Electron Spin Resonance Studies of Biochemical and Biological Systems," 1961-1962 (Box 67)
      - "Electron Spin Resonance Studies of Free Radical Intermediates in Oxidation-Reduction Enzyme Systems," 1959-1962 (Box 67)
      - "Electron Spin Resonance Studies of Photosynthetic Systems," 1960 (Box 67)
      - "Environmental Health: A New Challenge to University Education and Research," 1967 (Box 164)
      - "Equations for the Incorporation of Radioactivity," Townsend, 1962 (Box 67)
      - "EST Studies on Azotobacter Cultures," 1960 (Box 67)
      - "Estimates of Radiation Dose from SR90 due to Fallout," 1959 (Box 67)
      - "The Fallout Problem," 1958 (Box 67)
      - "Fast Kinetics of Unpaired Electrons in Photosynthetic Systems," 1963 (Box 67)
      - "The Formation of Infectious Nucleoprotein From Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein and Tobacco Leaf DNA," 1956-1957 (Box 67)
      - "Free Radicals in Biological Materials," undated (Box 67)
      - Free Radicals in Biological Systems, book review, 1961-1962 (Box 67)
      - "Free Radicals in Biology," 1961 (Box 67)
      - "Free Radicals in Heart Muscle Mitochondrial Particles," 1960, undated, (2 folders) (Box 68)
      - "Free Radicals in Surviving Tissues," 1961 (Box 68)
      - Gene paper correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 68)
      - "Government Research Grants: Effect of the New Procedures," 1963 (Box 68)
      - "The Hazard of Fallout," 1958 (Box 164)
      - "Heterogeneity of the Products of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Biosynthesis," 1962 (Box 68)
      - "If by Land, Sea and Air," 1970 (Box 164)
      - "In Defense of Biology," 1961-1964, (2 folders) (Box 68)
      - "Is DNA a Self-duplicating Molecule?" 1961-1962 (Box 68)
      - "Is DNA the Secret of Life?" 1964-1965 (Box 69)
      - "Is Science Getting out of Hand?" 1962-1963 (Box 69)
      - Journal of General Physiology, manuscripts submitted, 1952-1953 (Box 69)
      - Legacy of Hiroshima by Edward Teller, book review, 1962 (Box 69)
      - "Light-Induced Free Radicals in FMN and Flavoprotein Enzymes," 1958, undated (Box 69)
      - "Light Induced Paramagnetism in Chloroplasts," 1956 (Box 69)
      - "Linear Analysis of Tobacco Mosaic Virus," 1958 (Box 69)
      - "Linear Biosynthesis of Tobacco Mosaic Virus: Changes in Rod Length During the Course of Infection," 1962 (Box 69)
      - "Linear Biosynthesis of Tobacco Mosaic Virus: Development and Test of a Model," 1962 (Box 69)
      - "Linear Biosynthesis of Tobacco Mosaic Virus: Evidence that Short Rods are Natural Products of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Biosynthesis," 1962 (Box 69)
      - "Linear Biosynthesis of Tobacco Mosaic Virus: Incorporation of C14 into Rods of Different Lengths," 1962 (Box 70)
      - Manuscript reviews, 1955-1961 (Box 70)
      - "Microspectrophotometry," undated (Box 70)
      - Miscellaneous manuscripts, 1949-circa 1965 (Box 70)
      - "The Molecular Origins of Biochemical and Biological Specificity," 1964 (Box 70)
      - Nature, manuscripts, 1951-1954 (Box 70)
      - "The Non-virus Proteins Associated with Tobacco Mosaic Virus," 1954-1955 (Box 70)
      - "The Nucleic Acid and Protein Content of Mosaic Areas of Leaves Infected with Tobacco Mosaic Virus," S. Wagenaar, undated (Box 70)
      - "Properties of Infectious RNA Preparations obtained from Tobacco Mosaic Virus by a Heat Method," J. Lippincott, 1959-1960 (Box 70)
      - "The Proteins Synthesized in Tissue Infected with Tobacco Mosaic Virus," undated (Box 70)
      - "Rapid Biosynthetic Incorporation of C14 Labelled Amino Acids into Tobacco Mosaic Virus," 1963 (Box 70)
      - "Reactivation of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Infectivity in Mixtures of Virus Protein and Nucleic Protein," 1955-1956 (Box 70)
      - "The Reconstitution of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Components," 1956 (Box 71)
      - Record of publication of articles, 1955-1972 (Box 71)
      - "Relationships between Tobacco Mosaic Virus and the Non-virus Proteins," 1954-1955, 1965 (Box 71)
      - "The Replication of Tobacco Mosaic Virus: A Re-examination of Theories," 1959 (Box 71)
      - "The Replication of Tobacco Mosaic Virus: Kinetics of Virus Protein and RNA Biosynthesis," 1958-1959 (Box 71)
      - Requests for reprints, 1960-1966 (Box 164)
      - Requests for reprints, 1963-1964 (Box 71)
      - Requests for reprints, 1970-1972 (Box 73)
      - "The Roles of DNA in Inheritance," 1963-1965 (Box 71)
      - "Science and the Race Problem," 1963 (Box 71)
      - Science, manuscripts and reviews, 1949-1962, (2 folders) (Box 71)
      - Scientific American, manuscripts, 1956, undated (Box 71)
      - "Scientific Statesmanship," 1962-1963 (Box 72)
      - Subcommittee on pathology, National Academy of Sciences, 1963-1965 (Box 72)
      - "Variations in the Nucleic Acid Composition of Tobacco Mosaic Virus," 1956 (Box 72)
    - Reprint file, #1-#60, 1948-1961, (2 folders) (Box 72)
    - Reprint file, #61-#112, 1962-1969 (Box 73)
  - Book file
    - The Closing Circle
      - Bankers Magazine article, 1971 (Box 85)
      - "A Bulletin Dialogue on The Closing Circle ," by Commoner. Science and Public Affairs: Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1972, May, (6 folders) (Box 84)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1973, (2 folders) (Box 85)
      - Correspondence with Bibler and copy of draft, 1971 (Box 83)
      - Draft 1 (Box 74)
        - Binder of complete draft, circa 1970, (2 folders) (Box 74)
        - Chapters 1-4, circa 1970, (6 folders) (Box 74)
        - Chapter 5, circa 1970 (Box 75)
      - Draft 2, circa 1971, (6 folders) (Box 75)
      - Draft 3, 1971, (5 folders) (Box 76)
      - Draft 4, circa 1970 (Box 77)
      - Draft 5, circa 1971, (4 folders) (Box 77)
      - Draft 6, 1971, (3 folders) (Box 78)
      - Draft 7, chapters 1-3, circa 1971, (4 folders) (Box 80)
      - Draft 8, circa 1971 (Box 83)
      - Draft 9, circa 1971, (2 folders) (Box 83)
      - Draft 10, circa 1971, (3 folders) (Box 84)
      - Draft acknowledgements, circa 1971 (Box 78)
      - Draft chapter summaries, circa 1971 (Box 78)
      - Draft, "corrected," 1971, (6 folders) (Box 79)
      - Draft endnotes, circa 1971, (2 folders) (Box 78)
      - Draft preface for 2nd edition, 1974, (2 folders) (Box 84)
      - Galleys, corrected, 1971, (3 folders) (Box 81)
      - Jacket copy, 1971 (Box 78)
      - New Yorker article based on book, 1971 (Box 83)
      - "On The Closing Circle. Response," by Commoner, Environment magazine: correspondence, drafts, galleys, 1972, (4 folders) (Box 82)
      - Permissions, 1971-1977 (Box 85)
      - Promotional trip to London, England, 1972 (Box 85)
      - Prospectus, 1970 (Box 76)
      - Prospectus, 1970 (Box 78)
      - Publicity and sales, 1971-1976, undated (Box 85)
      - Publishers (Box 85)
        - Contracts, 1970-1972 (Box 85)
        - Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 85)
      - Reviews, 1973-1974 (Box 85)
        - Consumers Union edition, 1973 (Box 86)
        - Copies mailed to, 1971-1973 (Box 86)
        - Foreign editions, 1970-1977, (2 folders) (Box 86)
        - Italian edition and award, 1973-1977 (Box 86)
      - Translation proposals, 1974 (Box 86)
        - Draft in binder, 1970, Dec., (2 folders) (Box 87)
        - Galley in binder, circa 1971, (2 folders) (Box 87)
    - Politics of Energy
      - Contract, 1979 (Box 95)
      - Correspondence, 1979, (3 folders) (Box 94)
      - Drafts, circa 1979, (17 folders) (Box 91)
      - Drafts, circa 1979, (13 folders) (Box 92)
      - Drafts, circa 1979, (8 folders) (Box 93)
      - Drafts, outlines, and notes, 1978-1979, (6 folders) (Box 96)
      - Drafts, 1978-1979, (5 folders) (Box 97)
      - Drafts, circa 1979, (5 folders) (Box 98)
      - Drafts, circa 1979, (2 folders) (Box 100)
      - Galleys, corrected, 1979 (Box 99)
      - Miscellany, circa 1979, (2 folders) (Box 100)
      - New Yorker articles based on book (Box 95)
        - Drafts, 1979 (Box 99)
        - Galleys, 1979 (Box 99)
        - Letters from readers, 1979, (4 folders) (Box 95)
    - Poverty of Power
      - Acknowledgements, circa 1976 (Box 119)
      - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1976 (Box 117)
      - Bantam Books, paperback edition, 1977 (Box 117)
      - Book tour, 1976 (Box 117)
      - Chapter lists, 1975 (Box 119)
      - Copies mailed to, 1976 (Box 117)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1979, (4 folders) (Box 118)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 119)
      - Drafts, 1975, undated, (4 folders) (Box 101)
      - Drafts, 1975, (7 folders) (Box 102)
      - Drafts, chapters 1 and 2, 1975, undated, (12 folders) (Box 104)
      - Drafts, chapter 2, circa 1975, (10 folders) (Box 105)
      - Drafts, chapter 3, circa 1975, (7 folders) (Box 106)
      - Drafts, chapters 3,4, and 5, 1975, undated, (16 folders) (Box 107)
      - Drafts, chapters 7, 8, and 9, circa 1975, (23 folders) (Box 108)
      - Drafts, chapter 7, circa 1975, (15 folders) (Box 109)
      - Drafts, chapter 5, circa 1975, (10 folders) (Box 110)
      - Drafts, chapter 6, circa 1975, (12 folders) (Box 111)
      - Draft, chapter 11 "The Argument," 1975 (Box 119)
      - Drafts, endnotes, circa 1975, (3 folders) (Box 120)
      - Drafts, full, 1975, (5 folders) (Box 112)
      - Drafts, full, 1975, (3 folders) (Box 114)
      - Drafts, working copy, 1975, (4 folders) (Box 113)